[SPEAKER_02]: So, the first step is that authenticity.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know for yourself what's wholesome, as wholesome, what's unwholesome, as unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you can see increasing in you, or decreasing in you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you can see circumstances being responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes not.
[SPEAKER_02]: When they are, you know, ah, all I have to change is the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they're not, if it's not the circumstances to be blamed, then you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not making enough effort, or I'm becoming careless, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But either way, it comes down to being self-transparent, and you seeing through that, and then knowing how to act.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, as I said, if you see it at, like, initial stage, you don't need a great amount of effort to keep it on the course.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, for somebody, sure, Tudung like this might be great, but then also living in a secluded kuti is great.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I don't have a secluded kuti, and I'm living in Tudung, well, I'll just keep doing what I have.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's good enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I have secluded kuti, and I don't have to go to them, well, I'll keep doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not black and white, and it's determined, basically, by your mindsets that you need to be honest with yourself about.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's often, actually, more about recognizing where unwholesome is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if there is no unwholesome, you most likely can practice wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, then you're doing fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you can, yeah, recognize the unwholesome, and keep that as faith, then, ah, then I can start moving more freely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I might happen, if that's my thing to go, you know, wandering, then I do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is no increase in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even the one that... and then you can, exactly within that, you can start refining it further.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, not just that there is no increase in unwholesome, there is also decrease in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I might do that more now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, if you don't know what you... if you don't know what you're doing, you're just trying to take an external form on... and expecting that that would... Well, most of the... most of the practice is exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people say that it's... that it is after practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's half a practice for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no such a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no such a thing as half a practice for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would replace both half a practice for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But yeah, people who project
[SPEAKER_02]: But other who misplace where the practice is, would hold on to the rules as practice, would hold on to the etiquette as practice, would hold on to observances as practice, as a virtuous practice, and it's nothing other than syllabatic paramount.
[SPEAKER_02]: And those same people would also, yeah, think circumstances of the practice, the monastery, the practice, keeping up with the routines in the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Never ever using any of those things, like, as a basis to reflect upon their mind themselves, choosing, intending, being responsible for all of that in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why, you know, you can spend 50 years in rows with the monk, following all the routines perfectly, doing everything perfectly, but never have a moment of proper reflection.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this slide is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just my mouth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's all there, but it won't go.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, as you asked before, what if the Second Tantra provided both wholesome and unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's unwholesome then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, you might have a like a
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to focus on not having the increase of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: By not having increase of unwholesome, that's already wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you take that further through your effort, through refining the circumstances, through refining that, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: Things you do throughout the day, you take that even further, so that it starts bringing decrease in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, all these terms are very general.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wholesome, unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: They need to be like that, general like that, because that's how you recognize them.
[SPEAKER_02]: You recognize the nature of unwholesome, the nature of wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: And exactly as we said before, for somebody walking around Charikas and Tudongs, but done out of complete restlessness, or some romantic ideals... And, you know, lots of monks do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lots of monks live quite a number of months really hard in the Tudongs or whatever else, and then they come in contact with civilization, they fall apart.
[SPEAKER_02]: They get angry, they get lustful, yeah, you visit, they're distraught, and you realize, well, what you've been doing all this time, walking around?
[SPEAKER_02]: You clearly haven't been practicing, because if you were, you wouldn't be affected by those unwholesome states, when they do eventually arrive.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the whole point is, whatever you choose to do, as a form of practice, is to be fortifying yourself, against the defilements, against the hindrances, and become stronger, and obviously develop wisdom through that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if, you know, somebody, again, perfect man, keeps all the routine, sits eight hours a day, and then he disrobes, what?
[SPEAKER_02]: What good would that do to him?
[SPEAKER_00]: It sounds like to me that you go into a situation, say, if you do wandering matters, where you don't come into contact with, maybe, things that stir you up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so you think, I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And people often would think that, yes, they would often think that if there is no transparency to recognize, okay, I'm fine now, but would I be fine if those things would arise, the unwholesome things?
[SPEAKER_02]: Would I be still fine?
[SPEAKER_02]: Would my mind be able to remain above them?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like, where we're going into this, going into the city, going into the village, every day, for his alms, he has to keep the strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where you can be.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, you might... often people would stop... stop and wonder, like, why are monks not allowed to grow their food?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can go and live on top of the mountain, growing your own food, and never see anyone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's exactly why.
[SPEAKER_02]: A lot of people use that as a form of escape, and never ever develop any wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: And on top of that, means the dhamma wouldn't actually be, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: But by being in some marginal contact with lay people, with people who are not monks, who are not practicing, they get to see it, they get to merit, and you actually get to be kept in check, like yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get to measure, you get to see whether your hindrances are rising, decreasing.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you just leave it in your mind, you get used to that, you have your own comfort, self-sustainable, you don't see any... oh, yeah, it's nice and romantic, but quite likely, you ain't going to be pushing yourself as hard as you should.
[SPEAKER_02]: But these things will prevent you from being complacent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there needs to be that kind of, ah, okay, no, I do depend on people, so I can't just run off.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't go down by your voice.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the middle of it, again, kākāsīna bhārka.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm going to test myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you need, if you already have a mental state of testing yourself, means you're already affected by the nature of those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you were not affected by nature of those things, well, if you're not affected by the nature of things you're testing yourself in regard to, you wouldn't need to test yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means, but if you're doubting whether you're going to be affected or not, means that's already a form of being affected.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you're doubting, oh, would these sites affect me, so I go and test myself, means, well, you're already affected by that doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you needed to prove that to yourself by going and testing you, going to the town or to a bar to see how you're going to react.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's just complete lack of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_02]: First of all, well, I'm trying to overcome this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, any exposure won't help.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even in the form of testing myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would I need to test myself if I know this needs to be all sums?
[SPEAKER_02]: And truly, overcoming something is when you become indifferent towards it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, even the idea of testing yourself means, well, why would I need to test my strength when I know I'm strong?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to go and keep fletching.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you doubt whether you're strong enough, then you have to go and keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what you want to do is not keep testing yourself in those silly, unwise ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: You actually want to remove the doubt in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You sealed it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And for as long as that remains sealed, nothing can enter it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, okay, so again, the last bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I'm, say, sitting in the kuchi, and I've calmed down,
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing's going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's this neutral, neutral feeling, generally.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain doesn't get that bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure doesn't get it much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I could even become complacent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I have to keep on looking where the effort is and isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: If everything is... if there are no disturbances of any kind, you do have suttas, you do have study, and you do have knowledge that you are not satipaṭṭhāna yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, there is a task for me to do, and all the circumstances are quite suitable, so I need to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I need to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I think even a state of just...
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, once you become a satipaṭṭhāna, get the right view, then, it's purely about recognizing wholesome and avoiding unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you stick to it, with restraint, with renunciation, with things that are required for different people, for different mindsets, different predispositions, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you stick to it, as Dhyanavira said, by practicing nekama-sankhapa, the thoughts of renunciation, intention of renunciation, you become like a tower of strength.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you know, the knowledge arises, and so on, and the person becomes higher, overcomes sensuality, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always everything needs to start with the right views.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no practice if there is no right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the right view makes the whole Noble Eightfold Path right, there is no such thing as you get this, you get that, you get this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have the suitable enough circumstances, get the right views.
[SPEAKER_02]: Spend the time trying to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, what happens after that?
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, there's like, again, many different ways you can get to the right view, pondering different things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, it's arrival at the same understanding of the same nature, but, yeah, people can arrive through contemplating different things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Contemplating wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is unwholesome unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_02]: Avoiding it, abandoning it, not tolerating it, not entertaining it.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the mind gets, like, get used to wholesomeness, you start acknowledging it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You start grasping the sign of your own mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you know, the impermanence and other things become much easier to sort of see in the right context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to ask you, like, I need a clarification about something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that...
[SPEAKER_01]: I read and I heard about this something called vāñchakadamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, sort of like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, I don't know how, like, for me, it sounded like an unfeelful or unwholesome nature of a thought or a process.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there was this article about... it was written by a monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was about having unwholesome, wholesome, and it's hard to be one chakra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, when you
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognize something to be wholesome, but in reality, it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example, like, let's say, this dog, like, goes on and try to catch that hair, and I stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, I'm saving the hare, so I do have good merits, or I'm sort of wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then again, I'm stopping the dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or in the process, I hit the dog.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what's the... what's the question there?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the context of that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there... What are you saying?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm asking, like, basically, is there a third, like, that sort of thing, like, pañcakadhamma, is there... is it a third
[SPEAKER_01]: sort of act, or sort of thought process, or is it still just unskillful and... A third, as opposed to wholesome, unwholesome, and then wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is meritorious, demeritorious, and neither meritorious nor meritorious.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, saving somebody, saving the life of... Well, again, sometimes something's more, something's less.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you just prevent the dog from eating,
[SPEAKER_02]: By preventing him from killing the hare, and you save the life of that that hare, that's obviously more wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's unwholesome if you're endocrine-eating.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not as unwholesome...
[SPEAKER_01]: But what if you kill the dog?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if you kill the dog, that's much worse for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you wouldn't have been killing the hare in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would have been the dog.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, again, you always need to look at it from your point of view, from the point of view of your action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, often the people, when they say, well, what if I kill one person who was about to kill 500?
[SPEAKER_02]: I saved 500.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it wasn't your responsibility to save 100, but it was your responsibility to not kill anyone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can't avoid that, as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, there are things that are neither pleasant or unpleasant, neither meritorious nor unmeritorious, neither good nor bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: A bit of both, or a bit of both?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, the one chakra means like... sort of like...
[SPEAKER_02]: But why is that relevant?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the... Because there was... in that article, it was divided into three sections.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than having wholesome or unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when it's wholesome or unwholesome, you know if this is wholesome, this is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not wholesome, it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: To me, it sounds like that article was talking about karma and then the ritual, if you part of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, oh, what you do, whether it's good karma or your bad karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more about, like, basically, um, like, the term vāñcaka means, um, vāñca as in, like, dishonest or
[SPEAKER_01]: um oh like uh to um
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, it's always in relation to an act of one kind or the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I suspect the whole article is written with that in mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, because you are...
[SPEAKER_02]: I do good, I'll be reborn in heaven, or I'm making merit.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, there are things that con you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You think you're doing good, but you're not.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not what we've been talking about in terms of wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wholesome and unwholesome, in terms of practice,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's what you recognize where your intention is rooted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether your intention is rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you recognize it's rooted in that, you do not do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, there is no neutral there, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's either good or it's either bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's what I meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you start seeing it like that, recognizing that it's not rooted in bad, that's what makes it good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good for the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what it means.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suitable for the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: From the point of view of karma, like, if what what you've done happens to be like this or like that, well, you don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you will know for sure that it's impossible to have an action, a deed done, while it was rooted in wholesome, not in unwholesome, to result in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you kind of bring it back to the source.
[SPEAKER_02]: You stop speculating about this particular thing means that, or if I do this, it will mean that, or... No, you just bring it really, really to the source, which is your intention, and then you know, my intention was not rooted in unwholesome, and you don't have anything to worry about.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't see that, then, yeah, then you have to worry about external and what other people say.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's good or bad, and then you try to get your way by pondering on those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, you just need to bring it down to the very point of origin, and then you will know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it... that's more about, again, about authenticity of each individual.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's absolutely prerequisite for everything right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, you can think of something as you're doing wholesome, but you're ignorant to a level... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you know, people think various things that are, like, socially or in the environment you live, accepted as good and wholesome, but you can be doing for convenient, wholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's those reasons that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the external, traditional way.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: What people say is that no one knows what else is in and of themselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's accepted, based on kind of some general norm, but it's not necessarily accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we think, what everyone else is doing, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever is okay with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, it's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is all right to do, but why are you doing it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, things can be externally neutral.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nobody would mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you know you're doing it for absolutely wrong reasons, so you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, sometimes things can be perceived negatively, externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: People can complain.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you know you're not doing it for the bad reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't have to worry about doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what it comes down to is that... Like, can I say, like, if it's... if it's wholesome...
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not wholesome, it is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not unwholesome, it is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it comes to the... your mind, where your intentions are rooted... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if it's neutral, then, okay, it's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all it matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: There can't be a neutral position, can it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it can be.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, certain... like, it doesn't affect anyone, doesn't affect you, doesn't affect others, in any way, in any shape or form, doesn't affect anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what about your volition, like... Well, even your volition doesn't... doesn't really affect... doesn't care.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't come from unwholesome, doesn't come from greed, doesn't come from...
[SPEAKER_02]: And in that sense, from the point of view of the practice, it's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: That neutral, it's wholesome, because, well, it's certainly not an obstacle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in between greed, aversion and delusion, and wisdom, generosity and
[SPEAKER_02]: The counter of greed, aversion, delusion is non-greed, non-aversion and non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, between those six, there's no other intention left, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're internally doing something,
[SPEAKER_01]: Either one of those things or a multiplication of those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: In terms of where it's rooted, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you have it like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because as you say yourself, and as you know, things can sometimes be a bit mixed.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact that it's mixed with unwholesome means, well, it's rooted in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where I wasn't clear about.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if it's rooted in neutral, in a sense of... well, there's no greed, but no non-greed either.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just complete indifference.
[SPEAKER_02]: By being like that, well, that's... that's awesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we'll be rooted in wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's... if there is no greed, it's a non-greed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is both greed and non-greed in regard to various things, well, that's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the difference there would come down to, like, the neutral feeling, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it's neither pleasure nor displeasure which is being felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's actually a lofty feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if that feeling is not known, it's unpleasant, it's delusional, it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that feeling is known, it's pleasant and it's wholesome and it's peaceful.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's... in itself, it's a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: In that sense, you would have like a neutral intention that doesn't resolve neither in good nor in bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if it's unknown as such, if it's not recognized for what it is, it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's recognized for what it is, it's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, great.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's... it's like your intention towards your feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the intention towards the feelings would be whether there is craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's a proper intention, there wouldn't be craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's improper, there would be craving in regard to whatever you feel.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good or bad or neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's a proper intention, there wouldn't be craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the proper intention?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, proper intention would be intention that would not lose the sight of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: For example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeps having... keeps...
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, acts from from having that introspection.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's that... what Nyanavirī wrote, a little quote.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't remember how to say exactly, but... An intention which doesn't imply craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a hard thing to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the... How does the rest of the question go?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the comment go?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well... An intention that doesn't imply craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because how can you...
[SPEAKER_00]: So if I... How can you intend something without craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: Without... That's just the duties towards feelings that one has.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, basically, the intention affected by ignorance will be
[SPEAKER_02]: It's kind of over-intending, you can say, which is when you're craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because there is no first beginning of your craving, you've always been over-intending.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the question is how to now learn, through that over-intending, through that craving for things, how to learn that actually intention can be without you needing to over-intend or do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's more like discerning within that over-intending intention what
[SPEAKER_02]: In itself, it's just intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is your doing on top of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: And recognition, for example, of the fact... Well, recognition of intentions as phenomenon is the very first step.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because most of the people, when they think intention, they immediately, ah, it's my volition, my direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, oh, intending this, intending...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always, it's like, like, like a direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like being directed that way, or this way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you don't see that as an arisen phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: You see that in rīgārtha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being manifest in rīgārtha is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, this has a reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm going there.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'm running away from that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't want that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's always this movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, seeing the movement of your intention as a still phenomenon is the very first step.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that means grasping the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Grasping the still sign of your moving mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thingness of your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, because changing while standing, the third characteristic, that's what movement is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether it's moving away, or towards, or away and towards, whatever, it's changing while standing, or rather, changing while remaining the same, resisting while changing, depending on whatever translation you want to use.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, even if there is a movement, towards or away, that movement is a thing,
[SPEAKER_02]: On a more general level, it's a single thing, single phenomenon, that it's sort of moving, changing on a particular level.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the movement is possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because on a different level, there is no movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: If everything is moving constantly, all the time, everywhere, there wouldn't be movement at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there wouldn't be a reference point.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, recognizing the nature of intention as a movement, but then being able to see that movement as an arisen thing, while it's moving.
[SPEAKER_02]: That will eventually, could lead to discerning, ah, the aggregate of intention, the phenomenon of intention, means even the intention, even the most, the quickest moving things of your mind, this, that, this, that, is only possible because it has a reason beforehand, as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: And over that, you have no say.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the only fact you can move
[SPEAKER_02]: Along a certain trajectory is because the trajectory has been given to you as a possibility to move.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you can never create anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just go along with what has arisen based on your choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize that even choosing left or right or up or down is only possible because all those directions are implied, given.
[SPEAKER_00]: All those intentions are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're completely enclosed within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's many, there's infinite number of intentions or directions you can go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there is the thing called intention, but it can move in different... You can say, let's say, there is an infinite number and infinite ways that intention can move.
[SPEAKER_02]: But all of those ways, all of those movements, are possible only if the intention has arisen beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is no intention, you can't conceive a movement of that intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's many... there's many intentions... You can say there is an infinite amount of movement of the given arisen intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not... you recognize...
[SPEAKER_02]: If the intention is the necessary cause, the phenomenon of intention, the presence of intentionality, is a necessary cause for any particular intention to be manifested, you recognize that any particular intention that you engage in, intentional intention, volition, whatever else, it's completely subordinate, completely dependent upon, completely determined by the phenomenon of intention being present.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you discern that, you will go, oh, well, you have absolutely no say.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can't intend the phenomenon of intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, you can't ever even conceive it to be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, because of upon that very thing that is inconceivable to be yours, your whole volition, your whole sense of self, your whole intentionality, stands upon, and it's completely determined by, and inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, by seeing that, then you're like, no matter how hard I will something,
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot... it's inconceivable to be taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: By fully discerning that impossibility, you'll stop taking it as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's... you're making a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's very much as we used to think you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where your sense of self sits, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that you're able to choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: I decide.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not... like, again, it's such a point.
[SPEAKER_02]: You see, even Bhattacharyya can get a hint of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might be able to choose, but when you're not able to not choose, because even when you say, I'm not choosing, you've just chosen that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're completely... What?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not to choose.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If so, I'm refraining from choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you just chose to not choose.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's another choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's always a possibility of your choice to refrain from choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you always end up...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is exactly?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the core of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you can't
[SPEAKER_02]: Choose your way out of choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't intentionally stop intending.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly, like, why you're condemned to kamma and then the eventual results of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't stop performing kamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't stop performing action, which means you can't stop experiencing results, no matter how far ahead they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why every intention, every action is intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you are condemned to such intentions that you know escape from, means, oh, result of it will be, it will result in action eventually, which means, oh, whatever then results of those actions are, will fall onto me, even I have no say over that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you never had say in it from the beginning, but by not knowing that,
[SPEAKER_02]: You just kept doing it, and kept appropriating it, which means whatever came as a result of it, later on, was also falling on your end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all acts have results, but for an arahant, they don't fall onto anybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, every action is intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, if you fully discern intentions, none of those intentions will be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, anything that those intentions result in, any acts done on current, won't be actually act.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because act, in the sense of kamma, is when the intention is appropriated and that it brought you to result in committing an action of a kind, which means then the results of those actions will also be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there will still be results.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't, like, you can say, oh, stop performing actions, because action, kamma, is bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't address, if you don't overcome, if you stop appropriate, if you don't stop appropriating your intention, means you're not really abstaining from any action, because from that point of view, even not performing an action is a form of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you find it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And sooner or later, you will be, you'll do something that will be resulting in one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see... can you see that intention directly?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you can see the movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you're expecting to stop the intention, to stop the movement in order to examine it, means you're already looking at the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can't have any...
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that there is a movement, means there is the phenomenon of movement that is still.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, literally, the trajectory you move has to be given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, there is no movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't have to stop the movement, you just have to recognize its nature, which is not moving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, the movement within that is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you call it an intention to be a movement?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, because that, like, if you want to phenomenologically describe it, it would be a movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: Movement of the mind, movement of the speech, movement of the action, of the body, depending how far it takes you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Choice is a movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And while... because while you... you have chosen some... you choose something and it... and it's... and it's... Well, that only implies the other things that you didn't choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But while I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sitting now, but I'm doing that walk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So my intention to sit is... remains
[SPEAKER_00]: As long as I don't choose something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will require you to stand up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm constantly... if I wasn't choosing to sit down, I would be doing something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, you have made a choice of sitting down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, you're not actively, constantly choosing to remain seated, but the fact that you have made that choice, and your body is still seated, means you're actively engaged in that choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're engaged, it's active, it's on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why the four body postures can be a good foundation of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because within that, now, any intentionality that you have will come from the intentionality of the seated body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means you can't
[SPEAKER_02]: All the other intentionalities that would exist on account of a different body posture are now absent.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't, like now, start intending things that would require you to run or stand up without running or standing up.
[SPEAKER_02]: So even if you think about it, that's not really an intention, because it's not really a possibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just an abstract thought that you think from the point of view of seated intentions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Body in this posture
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, so what's the duty then?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I'm watching my mind... Well, the duty is, you don't really have to be analyzing the domains of your intention and what's given and what's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: The duty is to see that whenever the movement is possible, whenever the movement is occurring, intention, volition, it's only because things in regard to which you're moving are given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a more general thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've seen impermanence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, any movement that occurs, that will occur, that has occurred, is within, is now seen within that inherent impermanence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, you do that long enough, any movement, no matter how quick, outleeting or whatever else, will not be taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's impossible to be taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you dwell on it long enough, and then it becomes apparent that there is no movement without a still thing being given beforehand, for which, just the fact it was given beforehand, you had no say in its origin.
[SPEAKER_00]: To be able to make a choice, you must have things to choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Options.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And those... Options would be more particular, like proliferation, but just the fact that to be able to make choice, you have to be able to move mentally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means, in order to move mentally, the mind needs to be there beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, instead of chasing the movement, you actually use movement like as an indication of the fact that the mind is still.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence the sign of the mind, cittanimitta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, long enough there, it uproots craving from... Well, craving is possible for as long as there is sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, I am intending this means, basically, I'm craving this.
[SPEAKER_02]: But once you start realizing that that's completely redundant, and that actually you can be intending and moving as a result of the, you know, five aggregates doing just that, on their own, not requiring you,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you won't.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't be needing to crave anymore, in any words.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I suppose the question comes up many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I'm not the one intending, then who's going to be responsible for the choices?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: The question who implies someone and the implication of someone means, well, the sense of self is still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether you have that sense of self as internally or externally or both, it's still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, ah, well, if it's not me, who is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Means, well, the general, then the nature of the self-view is still there, because now you're looking for somebody else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you start seeing that even that movement, that looking, that intending, that thinking, is possible only because thing is given before, and you just start including everything properly, and if you do long enough, then it will sort of...
[SPEAKER_02]: You cancel out the things that were never meant to be there in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your sense of self, craving, and all that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because none of that is required.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's completely redundant.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why we refer to it as a parasite.
[SPEAKER_02]: Upon... gratuitous parasite, but completely beginningless.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's no first point that ignorance has manifested before which you were not ignorant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, ignorance is not supposed to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not required.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, when you know that, you're not ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no, no, no, no, no, no space in between.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either you're ignorant or you're not ignorant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Knowing that ignorance has no room, removes ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Vijaya and avijaya, you can't... Knowing that you're seeing things in the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, knowing, for example, that you can't own things in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not knowing that makes you own them, through that not knowing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence a vijja is responsible for your sense of self, for your appropriation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Knowing fully and discerning fully that you can't actually own them, means vijja is responsible for your disowning and complete removal of appropriation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will know that you can't own them and you see them fully determined always by that which is arisen beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not saying that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever arises will be determined by this, that has arisen beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I can't even conceive to own it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way you can conceive to own it is when you forget that it's determined by that which has arisen beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's not tricky.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the practice is in discerning.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the whole pathicinam part is discerning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, discerning the connection between the two.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the connection is that connection of dependence, determination, being determined by, being inseparable from, saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's not, there is nothing else.
[SPEAKER_02]: In your experience, then, the five aggregates, whether put it in another hand, whatever you've been experiencing or not, it's just the five aggregates, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you want to discern the way they arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, within that which you already have, which you've been experiencing, within that, you need to start discerning the right things.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the the correct instruction is absolutely crucial.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can have all the right attention, proper ayoniso, manasikāra, proper attention in your life, if there is nobody telling you what you need to attend properly, how, you simply won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't know how.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is no immediate confirmation whether it's right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only after repeating it for five hundred thousands of times, then the confirmation, ah, okay, yes, I see this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see the direct connection.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you would be repeating something,
[SPEAKER_02]: Five hundred or thousands of times, that doesn't bear any fruit initially.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only if somebody tells you that you should keep repeating it, that eventually will show you the fruit.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you can't stumble upon dhamma accidentally.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't accidentally become a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, you had all the luck.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just thought the right thing at the right time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to think the right thing at the right time for thousands of times.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just repetition, repetition, repetition, repetition.
[SPEAKER_02]: Until it wears out, the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it's worn out sufficiently, for you to see over it...
[SPEAKER_02]: Imagine, again, like tall trees, you can't see anything from, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you're just hacking away, and hacking away, and hacking away.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you still don't see anything, because it's tall trees still.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tall bushes, tall everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you have hacked away sufficiently, you start to see.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you know, oh, this hacking is actually working, because now I have a degree of confirmation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's sotāpaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: You keep hacking further, now you know for sure, you have it confirmed for yourself that this hacking works in such and such way, and you keep doing it, and then eventually you'll see enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll see all you need to see.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if nobody tells you...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you can stop and think for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: If nobody tells you that repeating something, a way of attending things, a way of reflecting, if that is the right thing, and if you don't have faith in what they told you is the right thing, I mean, what are the chances of you, yourself, doing something right, that you don't know is right,
[SPEAKER_02]: And then doing exactly the same thing on and on and on and on for no apparent reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: For absolutely no apparent reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because nobody told you externally you should be doing nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: While everything, your whole experience is directed completely the opposite way.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's literally impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's impossible for somebody to arrive at the right view just by accident.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if somebody says, oh yes, it happened.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've done this one retreat and it happened to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: You most likely know they don't know what they're talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it doesn't happen to you, you develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if there's some... if something you develop, if there is something that you developed, you will know how you developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, Sotāpanna knows that he knows.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's not just like, oh, yeah, it happened to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know how, I can't put it into words, but it happened.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's lots of nonsense.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a spiritual mystical talk.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you've done something for thousands of times internally, and then you start to... then you have to confirm for yourself that it works, that it's freeing you from suffering directly here and now, then you will know that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will know how to... no matter how non-eloquent person you are, you'll still be able to say at least that which you repeated thousands of times, how you've done it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why the utterance of another is one of the two factors for the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: The other one is proper attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you got the utterance and then you keep properly attending it on and on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't have proper attention, you can have all the right utterance of other people all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: As you know, sometimes people did.
[SPEAKER_02]: They lived with... near the Buddha all the time, but never became anything, because they never properly attended.
[SPEAKER_00]: Proper attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, proper attention is all this what we've been talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Proper intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you need to know, or you need to... well, I'm sure you know, but you need to keep in mind that it's not... it doesn't happen overnight, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I just need to do it once rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It happens if you just keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like drilling, training, drilling.
[SPEAKER_02]: The simile, the simile of the axe handle in the sutra is about a carpenter who uses his axe every day.
[SPEAKER_02]: He doesn't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, he says, basically, the wooden axe, wooden handle, he uses it every day.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, each time, you know, he grips it, he's wearing it down.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't look at it and say, ah, today I wore down my handle this much or that much.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only after, you know, years of using it, one day you look and, oh, it's really thin.
[SPEAKER_02]: I really wore this handle down.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how ignorance is being removed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same sense, same feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you just keep doing it, and you keep doing it, and then there will be a point when you, oh, my ignorance diminished.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't say on a daily basis, oh, today, diminish this much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tomorrow, it will diminish this much.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can notice how much you've been attending on a daily basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attending?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, practicing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you can notice how much effort you've been putting on a daily basis, but you can't have a direct confirmation how much fruit that was there.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you do, then you will be more confident, and then you'll know, oh, yes, attending like this, as a result, it is confirmed confidence now.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, obviously, you're your own guide.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know what to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know how to do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But until then, you just have to keep doing it, and trying to make it as right as possible, without knowing whether it's right or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there's something you need to repeat for thousands of times, and then eventually recognize it as right, well,
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't know, before you repeated it thousands of times, whether it was right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you will know whether it was right or wrong, only if it was right, what you've been doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because then you go to criteria, whether it was right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's so important to discern the instruction, and really understand, try to understand it, and constantly just ponder and read the suttas, and talk with people you think that know the suttas, not just like a follower of everybody else, tell you the etymology, but really to try to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Trying to understand can lead to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: But one thing for sure, you can't understand something accidentally, without making an effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but being able to see these things in the sense, you know, some people, you can't be busy and be a busy person.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to dedicate your life to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to sit down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you need to dedicate your whole time to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, you can't... okay, you start contemplating and really getting into that mode, and then, you know, your phone rings, you have to go, you have to do this, you have to talk to that person, you have to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's done.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then the effort will be getting back to the starting point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not even starting, but getting back to a point where you can stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, no, you can't be busy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like even this this kind of life, wandering and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think wandering would work, if you get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you don't... when you know how to already attend things, and then you would be attending... because there are, like, it's obviously... it's physically challenging, it's tiring, it's uncomfortable, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get to see... You know, as nice as this forest is, there are lots of things that can bother one in any... in many ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: Insects, rain, rot, mud, whatever, whatever, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: But none of that would be a reason for you not attending properly, once you know how to attend properly.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you don't know how to attend properly, then, yeah, everything can be a distraction for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything can be a distraction for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you really want to minimize that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Still use the transparency that you have as Bhutujana to know, okay, I'm not just avoiding things, I'm not just going out to them because I'm restless, or I'm not just staying in my kuti because I fear discomfort.
[SPEAKER_02]: You find a balance of what you think is right, because you don't have a criteria what's right or wrong as Bhutujana.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you just have to, okay, do I have time to read the suttas?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I have time to meditate?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I have time to, like, contemplate?
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether I sit and meditate and contemplate, whether I walk, meditate and contemplate, I do have time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I have time, like, or rather, is the environment supporting me?
[SPEAKER_02]: Keep the sīla, keep the vinaya.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are no distractions, there are no unwholesome things happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's... those criterias are met.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's more than enough for somebody to be making effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, you know, you can be, oh, do I have enough time?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I don't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I not being this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'm being disturbed all the time by people.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, mingling with lay people all the time because I have to do this, I have to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's not wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, then you certainly won't be able to expect that you will have enough time to dedicate, like contemplating the meanings you grasp from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like constantly reflecting, constantly drilling and drilling and drilling and drilling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's a hard work as it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need any other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, by all means, before you get the right view, yeah, run away from the crowd, believe the world, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, later on, you might, you know, you might see even more.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, actually, I don't have to go this far from people.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't have to run on top of the mountain, because I'm fine here.
[SPEAKER_02]: My mind works well here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can still be progressing here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you definitely need to calm down and have still place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And
[SPEAKER_00]: Until such time, you're dry enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fair along like rhinoceros.
[SPEAKER_02]: The verse there refers to Sotāpanna, the Jnanavira quoted.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've gone beyond the witherings of the view of what we put on the monument.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nobody is my own guy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fair along like... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once you become your own guy, then fair along like rhinoceros.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not before that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because then you'll be fairing along like a dumb rhinoceros, bumping into trees and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.